Ever wondered about the differences between AI, ML, DL and
ds? Well, we're about to explore all of those today. Stay tuned.
So let's dive right into it. So AI vs ML vs
DL vs DS, a whole bunch of jargon, but we're going to clarify
all of that right up. So let's kick things off and take a look at
AI. So AI is really to do
with the ability of computers and machines to perform tasks
without explicitly programming them, otherwise known as the ability
for computers and machines to think by themselves.
So we typically break out AI into two key categories. These are
general AI and narrow AI. General AI typically
refers to the ability for a computer or a machine to be able to handle
a wide variety of tasks. Us as humans have
the ability to do a whole heap of stuff. We can see, we can speak,
we can hear, we can read, we can drive, we can do a whole range
of things. The ability for AI and machines to be able to do a
broad range of tasks similar to humans is what we typically refer
to as general AI. Now, we're still a little bit of
a while away from true general AI, but that's not to say it's not to
come. Now, narrow AI, on the other hand, is the ability for a
machine to handle a really simple or a really narrow range of
tasks. So that could possibly be the ability to translate speech to text,
or to classify images as having different categories, or the ability
to predict house prices, for example. All of these are examples of narrow
AI. So I'm going to be painting a bunch of visual imagery to help
you remember some of these topics. So the first one, in terms of breaking out
general and narrow AI, or the ability to remember general and narrow AI,
is just picture a really narrow or really skinny general in your mind.
So that way you know that there's two different types of AI, general and
narrow. Now onto the next topic, machine learning. So we've taken a look at AI
as being broken up into general and narrow. But how does machine learning fit into
this? Well, machine learning is the application of narrow AI
to specific tasks. Now, when we typically talk about machine learning,
we often compare it to traditional programming. So in traditional programming,
we supply data plus rules or conditional logic, and we get answers.
Now, in machine learning, on the other hand, we provide data plus
historical answers to get rules. We can then pass new data to
get new answers. So this is a bit of a change in the paradigm of
how computer scientists and machine learning engineers are building programs
these days. So what are some typical machine learning tasks?
Well, we broadly break out machine learning into three key
categories. These are supervised learning, unsupervised learning,
and semi supervised learning. So let's take a look at supervised learning
first. So supervised learning can be broadly broken out into two
key categories. These are classification and regression.
Classification is all to do with grouping things into categories
or labels. So say you had a big data set on all the different types
of pizzas you've liked and whether or not you've liked them, yes or no,
you, you could take that data and pass it through to a classification algorithm
to help it learn which types of pizzas you like. So then when you pass
through a new list of ingredients, it would be able to predict yes, you would
like that pizza, or no, you might not. Regression, on the
other hand, is all to do with predicting continuous variables. Some great examples
of regression are sales forecasting and predicting prices of
houses. So that encapsulates supervised learning. Now what about unsupervised
learning? Well, there's two key things to think about when you think of
unsupervised learning. These are really clustering. So the ability to
group people together. So say you wanted to group together high performing
and low performing and medium performing employees or high
value, low value, medium value customers, or a whole bunch of other different
types of data. But really it's all to do with grouping things together.
Now dimensionality reduction, on the other hand, is all to do with condensing
the features that you've got within a machine learning model. So, so a lot
of the time you might start out with a huge data set with a lot
of columns and you're not really sure which of those columns are important for your
machine learning model. Dimensionality reduction helps you reduce the number
of columns that you've got so that you can really focus on the important ones.
Now in order to remember supervised learning and unsupervised learning,
I'd suggest you remember this initialism Christopher Robin, Quarter duck.
So that way you remember classification, regression, clustering and dimensionality
reduction. So, so that takes care of supervised and unsupervised learning.
But what about semi supervised learning? Well, this is where reinforcement
learning comes in. Now reinforcement learning has four key things.
These are an agent, an action, an environment, and a reward.
It's similar to how you might choose to condition a dog. A dog
might do something, right and you might reward it with a piece of food.
In a similar way, we train reinforcement learning models to act
in a correct way in a given environment in, in order to learn appropriate actions
given that specific environment. Now the best way to Remember reinforcement learning
techniques is to remember Area 51. So that way you remember
agent, reward, environment and actions. Okay, so that takes care
of machine learning. Now we're going to delve a little bit deeper and get into
deep learning. So deep learning is a subset of machine learning
and really it's to do with performing machine learning tasks
using deep neural networks. Now, deep neural networks
and networks that have multiple hidden layers. So if you've ever
seen a diagram that looks sort of like this, this is a representation
of a neural network. But specifically in this case, this is a
deep neural network because it has multiple hidden layers.
Now the best way to remember deep learning is to remember that deep learning
is just like an onion, it has multiple layers. Little bit
like Shrek. Now that sort of covers AI, ML and DL.
What, what about data science? Well, data science is the practice that
sits over AI, ML and DL. It basically is
the art of extracting knowledge, insight and meaning from
data. The best way to remember the key components of data science are to look
at the CRISP DM framework. So the CRISP DM framework stands
for the cross industry standard process for data mining. And basically
it's a framework to help you along your way to producing really
good data science projects. Now, there's six key steps in
the data science process. These are business understanding, so understanding
the business that you're working with and the environment in which they operate.
Two data understanding, so understanding the data that you've got
on hand so whether or not you've got missing values, visualizing that
data and taking a look at some summary statistics. We've then got
data preparation. So this is all to do with getting our data ready for modeling.
In this step we might perform some feature engineering and create some new columns.
We might fill in some missing values and, and a whole bunch of other data
preparation steps, like for example, splitting our data into training and
testing. Next we've got my favorite, which is modeling.
This is all to do with training your machine learning algorithms to
perform well on a specific task. Once we've trained our models
in that modeling step, we get onto evaluation. Given that we've trained
our model, we want to make sure that it's going to work well once we
deploy it into the real world. This is what the evaluation step
is all about it. In this step, we try to check whether or not our
model is likely to perform well using specific evaluation metrics.
Now once we've gone through all of that, the last step is to go and
deploy our model. In order to deploy our model, we could release it as
a REST API, containerize it up, or save it as a binary so
we can go and use it elsewhere. Now a great way to remember Crisp
DM is to remember Barry drove directly to the Medical Emergency
department. That way you remember business Understanding data understanding
data preparation, modeling, evaluation, and deployment.
Now I've talked a lot about theory, but where do the Python packages that you
typically see used fit into this framework? Well, in terms
of data science, Numpy, Pandas, and matplotlib are probably going to be the most important
packages that you see floating around. Numpy and Pandas
help you traverse and explore your data and really work with
your data in terms of performing manipulations and data preparation.
Matplotlib and Seaborn help you visualize that data and
explore it even further. Now, the most important library in terms of machine learning
is probably scikit Learn. So scikit Learn has been around for quite some time
and gives you a whole bunch of really powerful algorithms
and utilities to help use them to train your machine learning models.
Now deep learning is becoming increasingly popular and there's a large number of
libraries that can help you perform deep learning. Some of
which which are notable are TensorFlow, Keras, Pytorch,
and Theano, just to name a few. And that about wraps up AI vs
ML vs DL vs DS. Thanks so much for tuning
in guys. Hopefully you found this video useful. If you did, be sure to give
it a thumbs up and hit subscribe. Until next time.
Ever wondered about the differences between AI, ML,
DL and ds? Well, we're about to explore all of those today.
Stay tuned. So let's dive right into it. So AI vs ML vs
DL vs DS, a whole bunch of jargon, but we're going to clarify all
of that right up. So let's kick things off and take a look at AI.
So AI is really to do with the ability of computers and
machines to perform tasks without explicitly programming
them, otherwise known as the ability for computers and machines to
think by themselves. So we typically break out AI into
two key categories. These are general AI and narrow AI.
General AI typically refers to the ability for a computer
or a machine to be able to handle a wide variety of tasks.
Us as humans have the ability to do a whole heap of stuff. We can
see, we can speak, we can hear, we can read, we can drive,
we can do a whole range of things. The ability for AI and
machines to be able to do a broad range of tasks similar to humans is
what we typically refer to as general AI. Now, we're still
a little bit of a while away from true general AI, but that's not
to say it's not to come. Now, narrow AI, on the
other hand, is the ability for a machine to handle a really simple or
a really narrow range of tasks. So that could possibly be the ability to
translate speech to text, or to classify images as having different
categories, or the ability to predict house prices, for example.
All of these are examples of narrow AI. So I'm going to be
painting a bunch of visual imagery to help you remember some of these topics.
So the first one, in terms of breaking out general and narrow AI,
or the ability to remember general and narrow AI, is just
picture a really narrow or really skinny general in your mind. So that
way you know that there's two different types of AI, general and narrow.
Now onto the next topic, machine learning. So we've taken a look at AI as
being broken up into general and narrow. But how does machine learning fit into this?
Well, machine learning is the application of narrow AI to
specific tasks. Now, when we typically talk about machine learning,
we often compare it to traditional programming. So in traditional programming,
we supply data plus rules or conditional logic, and we get answers.
Now, in machine learning, on the other hand, we provide data plus historical
answers to get rules. We can then pass new data to get new answers.
So this is a bit of a change in the paradigm of how computer scientists
and machine learning engineers are building programs these days.
So what are some typical machine learning tasks? Well, we broadly
break out machine learning into three key categories. These are
supervised learning, unsupervised learning, and semi supervised learning.
So let's take a look at supervised learning first. So supervised learning can
be broadly broken out into two key categories. These are classification
and regression. Classification is all to do with
grouping things into categories or labels. So say you had
a big data set on all the different types of pizzas you've liked and whether
or not you've liked them, yes or no, you, you could take that data
and pass it through to a classification algorithm to help it learn
which types of pizzas you like. So then when you pass through a new list
of ingredients, it would be able to predict yes, you would like that pizza,
or no, you might not. Regression, on the other hand, is all to do
with predicting continuous variables. Some great examples of regression
are sales forecasting and predicting prices of houses. So that encapsulates
supervised learning. Now what about unsupervised learning? Well,
there's two key things to think about when you think of unsupervised
learning. These are really clustering. So the ability to group people
together. So say you wanted to group together high performing and low performing and
medium performing employees or high value, low value,
medium value customers, or a whole bunch of other different types of data.
But really it's all to do with grouping things together. Now dimensionality reduction,
on the other hand, is all to do with condensing the features that
you've got within a machine learning model. So, so a lot of the time you
might start out with a huge data set with a lot of columns and you're
not really sure which of those columns are important for your machine learning model.
Dimensionality reduction helps you reduce the number of columns
that you've got so that you can really focus on the important ones.
Now in order to remember supervised learning and unsupervised
learning, I'd suggest you remember this initialism Christopher
Robin, Quarter duck. So that way you remember classification,
regression, clustering and dimensionality reduction.
So, so that takes care of supervised and unsupervised learning. But what about semi supervised
learning? Well, this is where reinforcement learning comes in.
Now reinforcement learning has four key things. These are
an agent, an action, an environment, and a reward.
It's similar to how you might choose to condition a dog. A dog might
do something, right and you might reward it with a piece of food.
In a similar way, we train reinforcement learning models to act in
a correct way in a given environment in, in order to learn appropriate
actions given that specific environment. Now the best way to Remember
reinforcement learning techniques is to remember Area 51.
So that way you remember agent, reward, environment and actions.
Okay, so that takes care of machine learning. Now we're going to delve a little
bit deeper and get into deep learning. So deep learning is a subset
of machine learning and really it's to do with performing machine learning
tasks using deep neural networks. Now,
deep neural networks and networks that have multiple hidden layers.
So if you've ever seen a diagram that looks sort of like this,
this is a representation of a neural network. But specifically
in this case, this is a deep neural network because it has multiple hidden
layers. Now the best way to remember deep learning is to remember that deep
learning is just like an onion, it has multiple layers. Little bit like
Shrek. Now that sort of covers AI, ML and DL.
What, what about data science? Well, data science is the practice
that sits over AI, ML and DL.
It basically is the art of extracting knowledge,
insight and meaning from data. The best way to remember the key components
of data science are to look at the CRISP DM framework.
So the CRISP DM framework stands for the cross industry standard process
for data mining. And basically it's a framework to help you along your way
to producing really good data science projects. Now,
there's six key steps in the data science process. These are
business understanding, so understanding the business that you're working with
and the environment in which they operate. Two data understanding,
so understanding the data that you've got on hand so whether or not you've got
missing values, visualizing that data and taking a look at some summary
statistics. We've then got data preparation. So this is all
to do with getting our data ready for modeling. In this step we might
perform some feature engineering and create some new columns. We might fill in
some missing values and, and a whole bunch of other data preparation
steps, like for example, splitting our data into training and testing.
Next we've got my favorite, which is modeling. This is all to do with training
your machine learning algorithms to perform well on a specific task.
Once we've trained our models in that modeling step, we get onto evaluation.
Given that we've trained our model, we want to make sure that it's going to
work well once we deploy it into the real world. This is what the evaluation
step is all about it. In this step, we try to check whether or not
our model is likely to perform well using specific evaluation metrics.
Now once we've gone through all of that, the last step is to go and
deploy our model. In order to deploy our model, we could release it as
a REST API, containerize it up, or save it as a binary
so we can go and use it elsewhere. Now a great
way to remember Crisp DM is to remember Barry drove directly to the
Medical Emergency department. That way you remember business Understanding
data understanding data preparation, modeling,
evaluation, and deployment. Now I've talked a lot about theory, but where
do the Python packages that you typically see used fit into this framework?
Well, in terms of data science, Numpy, Pandas, and matplotlib are
probably going to be the most important packages that you see floating around.
Numpy and Pandas help you traverse and explore your data and really
work with your data in terms of performing manipulations and data preparation.
Matplotlib and Seaborn help you visualize that data and explore it
even further. Now, the most important library in terms of machine learning is probably
scikit Learn. So scikit Learn has been around for quite some time
and gives you a whole bunch of really powerful algorithms
and utilities to help use them to train your machine learning
models. Now deep learning is becoming increasingly popular
and there's a large number of libraries that can help you perform deep
learning. Some of which which are notable are TensorFlow, Keras,
Pytorch, and Theano, just to name a few. And that
about wraps up AI vs ML vs DL vs DS.
Thanks so much for tuning in guys. Hopefully you found this video useful.
If you did, be sure to give it a thumbs up and hit subscribe.
Until next time.